hey everyone welcome back to this Tosca
automation playlist and we are talking
about the API testing
we have also seen a lot of different
features which are available with the
Tosca API scan but until now we have
been only using the rest apis
but as you know there are different
types of apis which you can basically
test and verify and Tosca supports a lot
of different apis right so apart from
rest apis uh one of the most popular
apis as you know would be soap API right
so these are based on the soap protocol
and they use XML as a communication
Channel between the server and the
client right so we are going to look at
how we can scan the soap apis and how we
can verify them or create test cases
using the API scan and the commander
okay so for this I'm going to use an
example which is available with
tricentis and you can find it in their
API Services web page okay so let me
click on this URI so that we can scan a
particular URI it is already present uh
in my list so as you can see the first
one web
service.torscloud.com
calculator.svc and this is a soap based
API okay
so I can go ahead and scan this
and it is going to basically create uh
you can see different uh folders folder
structure and the API structure for the
calculator right so this API can be used
to basically perform different types of
calculations and it is a soap based
protocol okay
so um if we go here you will see under
calculator
there are different types of
calculations like add divide multiply
subtract right and if I open one of
these messages you will see here
this is the XML format not uh
not the Json format okay and that is
what is being used for any soap based
API okay
so in this you can basically do a add
operation right so I can put some number
like 10 here and then then here okay
and then I can just send the request
this is a post request type this is the
end point and this is the resource as
you can see right so if I now send this
request and you will see the response is
coming back uh status code is 200 okay
and it will be returning this payload
which is in again in XML format and the
result is 20 right
so in terms of uh how you can scan a
particular API whether it is soap or
rest there is no difference how you
basically uh perform the checks that may
be a little different because the
payload format is little different right
so in case of rest it may be in the Json
format but in case of soap it will be in
XML format right so that's the only
difference you will see between a rest
API and the soap API okay rest of the
things like scanning or basically
creating test cases or verifying the
results all remains exactly the same
okay
so now if I want to create a API test
case on my Tosca Commander you know the
process right so first select the API
message go to API test case and there
you will find API test case export
now this time around I'm going to show
you a different way of doing this right
so when we open the API scan from the
Tosca Commander it can directly import
this API message but right now I haven't
opened uh the Tosca Commander I have
used the Standalone version of the API
scan so let me export this and let me
show you how you can bring it back to
Tosca Commander okay
so let's go ahead and Export this as I
said earlier this will be saved as a
subset okay so it will be exported as a
subset so let's
name it as calculator
and let's save it here okay
now let's open Tosca Commander
and now let's go to our project and
there will be basically importing the
subset and then we will basically have
the test case for that particular API
message which we are trying to verify or
trying to create test cases from that
right
so this is our project and we can go to
our API testing component folder okay
and then inside this
or I can even create another component
folder just to make it uh basically
clear okay so let me call it
soap API testing
okay and now inside this I'm going to
import my subset okay
so we have to go to that particular
location where this was exported
and I saved it under API
this is the TSU okay
and once you import that now you will
see that it has created a import folder
right
and inside that you will have your API
scan
so whatever you have scanned the module
status cases exactly in the same format
the only difference is you need to
export and import if you have used the
API scan as a standalone version not
from Tosca Commander okay so this is the
difference
now
the rest of the process is still exactly
the same right so this time around you
need to select the notes which you want
to add or you want to add the response
you can do that right
so go ahead and click on ADD and it will
add the status code we can also add the
result because we want to verify that
okay so these two uh will add in the
response
and in the request we can basically add
these two nodes because we can enter
different input values right we don't
just want one input value to to be just
added we want to make it basically a
calculator which can take different
inputs and give different output right
so now if I go back to my test cases you
can see uh we have got this different
values which we can enter here in the
request and in the response we can
basically select any value so that we
can verify it right
so here it will be 200 okay and action
mode would be verify
and in the request what we can do is
we can basically enter any particular
value either 10 or I can either enter
something else also right so it will
give this a result but then how do we
verify this okay
so to do that
let's add some configuration parameters
where we can store these values and then
we can check whether the addition of
these two values is equal in the
response okay so what I'm going to do
here is I'm going to add some
configuration parameters okay
and let's go here and here is the test
configuration parameter
and I'm going to call it num1
and I'm going to give some value here
and then num2
okay and then let's change this okay so
what we are going to call this is CP
number
and CP num2
so this way you can basically configure
your values and not pass static values
all the time right so you can just
change the configuration values and then
send this request okay now there are
different ways of doing it I'm just
showing you one way okay now go back to
response and here we are going to use
some math calculation right to add these
two numbers so we are going to access
that CP
again number one
and then
we are going to add this and again CP
of num2
right and do take care of the start and
end brackets okay just to make sure this
correct
something seems to be wrong I forgot one
curly brace okay
okay so now it looks correct so what it
will do here is basically it will verify
whether the output of whatever we are
calculating using the math function is
the same as the API response output
right
so let's go ahead and execute this now
okay so run this in SketchBook and then
it is going to verify whether it has
correctly calculated the value using the
API okay so verification as I said
earlier is very important no matter what
you are testing either API or any type
of application right so you have to
verify what is being returned by that
particular functionality which you are
trying to test so as you can see uh in
the result the status code was verified
and the add result was verified if you
want to look at what was verified the
expected value and the actual value both
are same so the verification passed
and that way we could verify that the
response is actually what was expected
right
so this is how you can scan your soap
apis you can create test cases and you
can also verify the request and response
of your soap API messages right
so this can all be done in Tosca using
the API scan and tatoska Commander
similarly you can also try this with all
different types of apis which are
supported by Tosca
so that's all for this video I hope you
enjoyed it and you learned something new
today related to API testing and Tosca
do tune into our channel to watch more
such videos uh in the coming updates
if you have not subscribed to our
Channel don't forget to subscribe
because you will get notified about each
and every video which we add on Tosca so
that you can continue learning this
exciting new automation tool